# 你看 今天搞了一點小龍蝦哦
Look! Today I have some crayfish here,
# 才十來斤 也不是很多
not a lot, not even ten kilograms.
# 我們用來
We can make a,
# 用來燜 燜小龍蝦
stew, stewed crayfish.
# 前兩天吃沒吃過癮
We had some a couple of days ago. But it was not even close to meet my crave.
# 今天再搞了十斤回來吃
So we have another couple of kilograms today.
# 我去拔點薄荷
I'm gonna pick some mint.
# 你看 這個菜園 這是我家的哦
Look! This veggie garden, it belongs to me, you know.
# 你看 村里面幫我圍了個籬笆 這個很靚
Look! The villagers fenced it up for me. The fence is really beautiful.
# 一大圈都圍起來了
The whole garden is fenced up.
# 比較美觀
It looks better.
# 一種上去全部活了
Everything inside grows really well,
# 好快呀
and fast.
# 長得好荿盛啊 才一個月不到就長成這樣子
They grow really well. It's not even half a month, and they're already growing so well.
# 我摘點 摘點薄荷葉
Let me pick some, pick some mint.
# 你看這些秧苗
Have a look at these seedlings!
# 長得好快呦
They grow really fast!
# 才種下去不到
They were planted, not even,
# 不到半個月 就成長這樣子啦
not even half a month ago. And they're growing so well now.
# 可以哦
Not bad!
# 我家種了五六畝地哦 到時候就不用去買糧食了
We've planted thousands of square meters. We don't need to buy rice anymore.
# 自己收割 自己儲存
We can harvest and store our own rice.
# 一年到晚都有得吃
We'll have rice all year round.
# 好多草
So much grass
# 你看 就這個薄荷
Look! This is, mint.
# 都長那麼高啦
It's so tall now.
# 很嫩的哦 這個薄荷
It's really young and tender, the mint.
# 都是野生的
They are all wild,
# 沒人的
and belong to nobody.
# 沒人就可以經常來摘
So I can come as often as I wish.
# 你看 這種就是真正的薄荷
Look! This is authentic mint.
# 像這個就不是
But this one isn't.
# 看上去都不一樣的 這種
It looks very different, this one.
# 這個有毛的
This one is hairy.
# 而且它葉子小 你看 這個是薄荷
Its leaves are small too. Look! This is mint.
# 長得那麼近
They grow so close to each other.
# 長得那麼近 我都分的出來
I can distinguish them though they grow so close to each other.
# 你看這種 這種就是
Have a look at this one. Here it is.
# 像我們一眼就能看得出來
Everybody here can distinguish easily.
# 這裡好多
Here's a lot.
# 摘了那麼多 夠了
We have so much here. It's enough.
# 要回去啦 下大雨啦
We need to go back. A rainstorm is coming.
# 哎呀 好香 好濃的味道
Aya! The rich scent of mint is really nice.
# 下雨了 要走快一點
We need to be fast. It's already raining.
# 下那麼大的雨 幸好我跑得快 要不然都變落湯雞了
It's raining cats and dogs. Fortunately we ran fast. Otherwise we would all get soaked.
# 柴也濕了
The firewood gets all soaked.
# 那些全部濕掉了
Those are all soaked.
# 我用那個煤氣
I'm gonna use gas.
# 煤氣來煮
I'll cook with gas.
# 這裡有煤氣
Here's the gas.
# 放郅哪裡 放這裡來
Where should we put it? Here?
# 就這樣
That's it.
# 這龍蝦都是 嫩的
The crayfish are all, pretty young.
# 把它先洗一下
Let me wash them first.
# 現在下雨呀 我們把蝦線取掉就好了
It's raining now. We're gonna simply remove the veins.
# 這個龍蝦很乾淨的
These crayfish are very clean.
# 你看
Look!
# 就這樣子 這樣子就很好搞了
So, so then it's pretty easy.
# 這小龍蝦要把這個
The crayfish, we need to,
# 抽出來
take this part out,
# 然後把尾巴 尾巴上這個蝦綫 先抽出來
and then the tail, the vein on the tail, we need to take it out first.
# 這樣就很乾淨
Then it's very clean now.
# 全是肉哇
There's only meat.
# 不用啃
There's no need to gnaw.
# 別動
Freeze!
# 揮舞著它的兩個鉗子
It's swinging its two pincers.
# 搞定
Done!
# 誒呦 來的那麼痛的
Ayo! It hurts! It pinches so hard!
# 誒呦
Ayo!
# 夾人的這個
It pinches!
# 這個很好吃的哦
This is really tasty, you know.
# 昨啦 胡韋汝 你眼神不對呀
What happened, Hu Weiru? You're showing the wrong facial expression.
# 要笑
You should smile.
# 把這個小龍蝦
I'm gonna wash,
# 先洗一下
wash the crayfish first,
# 洗多幾遍
wash them a few more times.
# 放點鹽去洗一下
Let me wash them with some salt,
# 整包放下去
I'll put the whole pack.
# 沒啦
No more
# 更入味了 這樣
They would be, more flavourful.
# 全部都 全部都不動了
None of them, none of them is moving anymore.
# 把這個 薄荷也洗一下
Let me, wash the mint as well.
# 拿到那邊去
I take them over there.
# 搞點薑
Get some ginger
# 像天使的翅膀一樣
It's like the wings of an angel.
# 它這樣像翅膀一樣的 會飛的
They are just like wings and can bring you to the sky,
# 小天使啊
like a little angel.
# 現在多搞點薑
I need a bit more ginger now.
# 蒜包呢
No garlic?
# 等一下
Moment
# 哈
What?
# 先等一下
A moment
# 有蒜包吧
We have garlic.
# 搞點大蒜
Put some garlic.
# 這個蒜包就不用剝啦 直接這樣拍就好啦
The garlic doesn't need to be peeled. We can simply crush it right away.
# 先把火燒起來
Let me light the fire first.
# 過一下水
We're gonna boil the crayfish.
# 過一下水再來
Blanch them for a while, and then,
# 再來炒
we'll fry them.
# 加一點水
Put some water.
# 先把小龍蝦 小龍蝦放下去哦 要過一下水
I first put the crayfish, the crayfish into the wok. I wanna blanch them for a while.
# 翻都翻不動
It's so packed.
# 可以
Alright!
# 剛剛好一鍋
One whole wok
# 先把它蓋一下
Let me cover it first.
# 水還沒開
Not boiling yet
# 先煮一下它們
Blanch them for a while first.
# 哇 鮮紅的
Wa! Shinning red!
# 出鍋啦
It's done!
# 我去清洗一下
I'm gonna wash them.
# 把這個
I pour them,
# 倒出來 清洗一下
pour them out. So that I can wash them.
# 哇 好香哦
Wa! It smells really great!
# 你看 這樣很乾淨啦 這樣
Look! Then, it's very clean now.
# 把油放進去
Pour the oil into the wok.
# 全部倒完
No more
# 先把這個生薑
I first put the ginger,
# 生薑放下去油炸一下這個生薑
the ginger into the oil and fry it for a while first.
# 把那小龍蝦倒下去
Then I pour all the crayfish into the wok.
# 把這個大蒜也放下去
And the garlic as well
# 放點鹽
Put some salt
# 鹽要稍微放多一點
I need a little bit more salt.
# 把下面的撈上來 多放點(鹽)
Let me flip those at the bottom to the top, and put some salt.
# 這差不多啦
Almost there
# 把這辣椒哇 香葉那些清洗一下
Let me wash the chilli, the bay leaves or whatever.
# 等下要淌一點
They need to be rinsed.
# 撈不起來那些 拿個簍子來
I can't scoop them up. I need a sieve.
# 把它放在這裡 等下跟著一起放
Leave it here. Then I can put everything into the wok.
# 這樣就放進去啦
So they're put together now.
# 把這全部一起放進去
Let me put them all into the wok,
# 一起燜啦
and cook them together.
# 全部放下去
Put them all into the wok.
# 鍋都沒那麼大
The wok can hardly hold them all.
# 這種薄荷很香的哦 一放下去就有薄荷的味道
This kind of mint smells really great. I can smell it once they're in.
# 放點料酒
Put some cooking wine.
# 哇 真的好香啊
Wa! It smells really great!
# 有點聞到香味啦
The aroma is now coming out.
# 我要加點水 加點水
I wanna put some water, some water,
# 然後就讓它燜
and then cook it for a while,
# 燜個半個小時
for half an hour.
# 放點
Put some,
# 放點水燜一下
put some water and cook it for a while.
# 多的就不要
Not too much
# 蓋起來
Cover it.
# 大火 燜半個小時
Cook it for half an hour, on high heat.
# 加點醬油
Put some soy sauce.
# 哇
Wa!
# 現在都熟透啦
It's done now.
# 可以
Alright!
# 抬到那邊去
Let me take it over there.
# 嗯
Um!
# 可以喲
Not bad!
# 很入味
It's really flavourful.
# 現在這個 把那個蝦頭剪掉啦
Now, I mean, having the heads cut away,
# 就是不一樣
really makes a difference.
# 好吃嗎 叔叔
Uncle, does it taste good?
# 嗯 好吃
Um! Yes!
# 你看 這很好吃的
Look! It's really tasty.
# 嗯 我不喜歡吃辣的
Um! But I don't like spicy food.
# 嗯 可以可以
Um! Not bad, no bad!
# 下次我們再搞多點來吃
Let's have more next time.
# 剛好全部人都回來啦
Everybody is back now.
# 這蠻好吃的哦
It's rather tasty.
# 可以喲
Not bad!
# 很入味哦 是啊
It's really flavourful.
Yup!
# 大的不入味 這小的很入味
The small ones absorb the flavourings better than the big ones.
# 剛好還有一個西瓜
It just so happens that we have a watermelon here.
# 這西瓜不會自己爆呢
Why can't this watermelon crack open on its own?
# 哇 紅不紅
Wa! Is it red enough?
# 紅 是不是
It is, isn't it?
# 來 準備
C'mon! Get ready.
# 準備開始吃了啊
get ready to get started.
# 快點 邊拿
C'mon! Take one!
# 邊拿
Take one!
# 哎呀 這塊 最大塊的給你 快點
Ay! This one, the largest one is for you. C'mon!
# 快點吃
C'mon! Take one!
# 嗯 還有
Um. More coming.
# 好不好吃
Does it taste good?
# 好
Alright!
# 開吃 開吃
Let's start, let's start!
# 你幹嘛
What do you want?
# 要小狗狗是不是
You want the puppy, don't you?
# 小狗狗不要 它不吃
The puppy doesn't want it, doesn't like it.